<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Honos &amp; onus levitarum. Or, tithes vindicated to the presbyters of the gospel in a sermon preached at an archidiaconall visitation at Marleborough, in the diocese of Sarum, on the 10. of October. 1636. By B.P.</title>
            <title>Historie of tithes, or tithes vindicated</title>
            <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09057</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19348</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100345</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836188</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836188</idno>
            <idno type="VID">444</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09057)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 444)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1526:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Honos &amp; onus levitarum. Or, tithes vindicated to the presbyters of the gospel in a sermon preached at an archidiaconall visitation at Marleborough, in the diocese of Sarum, on the 10. of October. 1636. By B.P.</title>
                  <title>Historie of tithes, or tithes vindicated</title>
                  <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Turner, for William Webb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>B.P. = Bartholomew Parsons.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 427) on title page.</note>
                  <note>Another issue of STC 19347.5.</note>
                  <note>With cancel title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Joe Kilduff</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:444:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:444:1"/>
            <p>HONOS &amp; ONVS Levitarum. OR, Tithes vindicated to the Presbyters of the Goſpel: In a Sermon preached at an Archidiaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Viſitation at <hi>Marleborough,</hi> in the Dioceſe of <hi>Sarum,</hi> on the 10. of October. 1636.</p>
            <p>By <hi>B. P.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Honour the LORD with thy ſubſtance, and with the firſt fruits of all thine increaſe. <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 3.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>I give Tithes of all that I poſſeſſe. <bibl>
                  <hi>LUKE 18.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Let him that is taught in the Word, communicate unto him that teacheth in all good things. <bibl>
                  <hi>GAL. 6.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <p>ACADEMIA OXONIESIS</p>
               <figDesc>University of Oxford coat of arms and printer's device of William Turner</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by WILLIAM TURNER, for WILLIAM WEBB. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:444:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:444:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL SIR WILLIAM DODDINGTON of <hi>Breamer,</hi> in the County of <hi>Southampton</hi> Knight, A Mirrour of Pietie and Patience.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which <hi>Solomon</hi> maketh the children and husband of the virtuous woman to bleſſe her for, and praiſe her in, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daughters have done virtuouſly, but thou excelleſt them all,</hi> Prov. <hi>31.29.</hi> is without fawning or flattery (which God and all good hearts detest) appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to you; many ſonnes and daughters in our Church have done virtuouſly, in refreſhing
<pb facs="tcp:444:3"/>the bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>els of Gods ſervants, that ſerve him in the Goſpel of his Sonne, and casting of large gifts into his treaſury; but you have outrunne them all in our parts. For not onely the eye that ſeeth you, giveth witneſſe to you, but alſo the eare that hath heard you, yea heard of you, bleſſeth you for the good deeds you have done for the houſe of God, and the offices thereof, in restoring by way of free-will offering backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to the Church, thoſe impropriations of yours, of which you might have ſaid, we have a law of our land, and by that law I ought to hold the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; of which many a churliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> would have ſaid, <hi>Shal I take my bread, &amp; my fleſh, &amp; give it to men I know not whence they are? 1</hi> Sam. <hi>25 11.</hi> And the harts of most of the Clergie about you are inlarged, their mouthes are opened to pray for you with <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> prayer, <hi>remember him, O God, concerning this, and wipe not out the good deeds that he hath done,</hi> &amp; to ſpeak good of theſe worthy works of yours in the gates and chiefe places of concourſe. For if that one box of ointment which <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> poured on our Saviors head, be pronounced by our Saviour himſelfe to be a
<pb facs="tcp:444:3"/>good worke wrought upon him for his buriall, and injoyned to bee told for a memoriall of him, whereſoever the Goſpell ſhould be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched through the whole world, <hi>Matth. 26.13.</hi> much more may that grace of God beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, whereby the riches of your liberality hath abounded, to the restitution of the Tithes of thoſe Church-livings (which you had in your poſſeſsion, and which it was in the power of your hand to have kept back;) be publiſhed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed in this our Britaine world. All which as you have done not out of lightneſſe, vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, or to gaine popular applauſe (which you cannot looke after, having beene ſo long cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the world, and the world to you, both in your afflictions, and by your ſufferings, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God hath tried you as a beloved ſonne) but out of a conſcience truly informed out of the ſaving word of God, both of the lawfulneſſe and neceſsity of your act: So that God who hath promiſed that a cup of cold water given to a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, ſhall not loſe its reward, <hi>Matth. 10.44.</hi> and that whoſoever ſhall forſake houſes or lands for his name's ſake, and the Goſpels, ſhall receive ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold
<pb facs="tcp:444:4"/>more in this life, with life everlasting, <hi>Luke 18.30.</hi> hath not ſuffered one word of his good promiſe to faile in you, but in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath by other faire waies very plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully restored this loſſe (as the world would have accounted it) to you, and bleſſed you (as <hi>Iacob</hi> prayed for his ſonne <hi>Ioſeph, Gen. 49.25.</hi> with the bleſsings of heaven above, and of the deepe that lyeth under.</p>
            <p>Since then you have beene not onely a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, but a doer alſo of the duties preſſed in this diſcourſe, and brought forth much fruit in this kinde, giving to many others an example what they ſhould doe therein, as <hi>Eſau</hi> ſaid of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon to his father <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that God had brought it to his hands, <hi>Gen. 27.</hi> ſo may I, that God hath brought you to my hands, to whom I ſhould dedicate this part of my labours, wherein I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make it cleare (unleſſe it be to them that ſeeing will not ſee) that Tithes are as juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the portion and right of Gods Presbyters under the Goſpel of grace, as they were of the Prieſts of the moſt high God before the Law, and of the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> by Gods gift to them under the Law.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:444:4"/>Now the God of heaven, who hath given to you not onely to beleeve in his name, but alſo to doe ſo worthily in and for his Church, and to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſo many great afflictions, as a good ſouldier of Ieſus Christ, (wherein you have beene a true ſonne of <hi>Abraham,</hi> both in the meaſure of your ſufferings, and the eminency of your patience) make your comforts abound by Chriſt, as the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt have abounded in you, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you have ſuffered a while, filled up that which is behinde of the afflictions of Chriſt in your fleſh, and are come out of the furnace of affliction as his tried gold, beſtow upon you that crowne of life, promiſed to them that love him, and indure tribulations.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your ſervant in our LORD and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Saviour,</hi> Barthol: Parſons.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From the Rectory of</hi> Ludgerſhall, <hi>in the County of</hi> Wiltes, <date>
                     <hi>June 7. 1637.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:444:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:444:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEUT. 33.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Bleſſe, Lord, his ſubſtance, and accept the worke of his hands.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not unknowne to them that know any thing, that <hi>Moſes</hi> in this whole Chapter is <hi>totus in benedictionibus,</hi> ſpendeth himſelfe in bleſſings, and ſtandeth as it were upon mount <hi>Gerizzim, Deut.</hi> 27.12. to bleſſe the people of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> with a ſeverall bleſſing upon every Tribe amongſt them. The Text which I now propoſe unto you, is a little drop of that dew of grace which falleth here upon the head of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> which the Lord had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from among their brethren, <hi>to teach Jacob his judgements, and Iſrael his law, verſ.</hi> 12. And herein this man of GOD calleth upon the mighty JEHOVAH, who being the greater, can bleſſe the leſſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.7. whoſe bleſſing is a doing of ſome good<note n="(a)" place="margin">Dei bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicere eſt hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facere. <hi>Lucas Brug.</hi> in <hi>Matt. 25.</hi>
               </note>, beſtoweth ſome gift alwaies upon them that are bleſſed of him<note n="(b)" place="margin">Dei bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictio aliqui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muneris ſempe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his qui ab co le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedicuntur im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertit. <hi>Orig.</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rom. 12.</hi>
               </note>, maketh rich, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.22. and of whom whoſoever are bleſſed, they ſhall be bleſſed indeed, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid of his bleſſing of <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 27.33. To bleſſe, that is, to defend and multiply: for bleſſing eſpecially and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:444:6"/>is underſtood in multiplication<note n="(c)" place="margin">Benedicti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſolet max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e &amp; proprie intellig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Pſal. 66.</hi>
               </note>: according to which, <hi>Moſes</hi> telleth Iſrael <hi>GOD will bleſſe thee; and multiply thee, hee will bleſſe the fruit of thy wombe, &amp;c. Deut.</hi> 7.13, 14. <hi>His ſubſtance</hi>] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for ſo after our beſt tranſlators <hi>(quorum noman ſit in benedictione,)</hi> I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turne the word with many learned Interpreters<note n="(d)" place="margin">Calvin, Pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Borthaus, Chald. para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phr. &amp;c.</note>, finding for warrant hereof this word bearing the ſame ſenſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Beware leſt you ſay, my power, and the ſtrength of mine hand hath prepared me</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>this wealth.</hi> And <hi>Job.</hi> 20.15. <hi>Hee hath ſwallowed downe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>riches:</hi> then with others, his ſtrength<note n="(e)" place="margin">Vulg. e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it.</note>, his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and multitude<note n="(f)" place="margin">Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et. Jun.</note>; for the words are well gloſſed by <hi>Martin Borrhaus,</hi> as thou haſt adorned the Levites with the Prieſthood, ſo for the maintenance of this, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper their riches, which conſiſt in Firſt-fruits and Tithes<note n="(g)" place="margin">In loc. ut ſacerdotio or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſts Levita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, it a etiam ad iſtud conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>andum, opes illorum qua Cernuntur in pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nstiis &amp; decimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: and to accept, or, as <hi>Junius</hi> more fully, <hi>grato animo ſuſcipere,</hi> with a favourable minde to receive; and as the Greek phraſe runneth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to bee well pleaſed with <hi>the worke of his hands</hi>] ſo that howſoever hee ſhall many times ſpread out his hands unto <hi>a rebellious and gainſaying people. Iſa.</hi> 65. 2. <hi>goe unto a rebellious people that will not heare, Ezek,</hi> 2.3, 4. <hi>that altogether breake the yoake, and burſt the bands of the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ordinances in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Jer.</hi> 5.5. and ſo may ſeeme to labour in vaine, and ſpend his ſtrength in vaine, and for nothing, <hi>yet his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be with the Lord, and his worke with his God, Iſa.</hi> 49.4.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the right dividing of theſe words, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. and to ſhew how they are <hi>profitable for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. the giving of ſatisfaction to two queſtions that lye in the way, ſhall be as a word ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in due ſeaſon. Firſt, why the man of GOD more ſpecially poureth out a prayer for a bleſing upon <hi>Levies</hi> ſubſtance, than any other of the Tribes, unleſſe it be <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:444:6"/>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> upon whom the bleſsings alſo of his father prevailed above the bleſsings of his progenitours, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.26. Secondly, why he prayeth not rather that the worke of <hi>Levies</hi> hands ſhould be bleſſed by GOD, than that it ſhould bee accepted of him? Of either a word.</p>
            <p>For the firſt. Is there not a cauſe, nay a double cauſe, why he ſhould thus ſtrive in prayer? why with <hi>Jacob</hi> he ſhould not let the LORD goe, unleſſe he gave a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.26. to <hi>Levie,</hi> ſubſtance? Firſt, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of <hi>Levi</hi> himſelfe. This prayer (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>) ſeemeth ſecretly to be oppoſed to that penury which would come upon the Levites, unleſſe GOD had provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them food by ſome other meanes, than by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of their fields. They were deprived of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon inheritance, and GOD himſelfe was their poſſeſsion. Therefore that their eſtate might not be troubleſome to them, <hi>Moſes</hi> miniſtreth a comfort, and biddeth them expect from GOD all abundance for ſufficient food, and promiſeth that his bleſsing ſhall be in ſtead of a large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue<note n="(h)" place="margin">Videtur hac precatio tacite opponi penuriae qua Levitas manebat, niſi aliunde illis ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum ſuppeditaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet Deut, quam ex agrorumpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventu. Privati erant commun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hereditate, &amp; ſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deut era<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> illis pro lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundio. Ergo n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> illis moleſta ſit ſua conditio, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latium adhibet Moſes, &amp; tubet a Deo expectar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> copiam quae ad victum ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat, ac promit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem ube<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rims provent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o fore. <hi>Calv.</hi> in loc.</note>. The other for the conſternation of <hi>Levies</hi> enemies, thoſe Harpyes, who as the Poet ſaith<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aeneid.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Diripiunt <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dapes, contactu<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omnia foedant</l>
               <l>Immundo,—</l>
               <l>Triftius haud illis monſtrum, nec ſavior ulla</l>
               <l>Peſtis, &amp;c.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>For the wiſedome of the Spirit of GOD, in whoſe eyes all things are naked and opened, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. and who declareth the laſt things from the beginning, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.10. foreſaw and foreſhewed, that the dayes would come, that men would be ſo farre from bringing offerings with the Iſraelites to the building of the Tabernacle, <hi>Exod.</hi> 36. that they would rather let it lye waſte, yea, make it waſte themſelves, that they might dwell in ſieled houſes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:444:7"/>
               <hi>Hagg.</hi> 1. So farre from asking with <hi>Saul, What preſent ſhall we bring to the man of God?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.7. that they will rather with <hi>Gehezi</hi> purſue them hard to pull ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what from them, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 5.20. ſo farre from providing with the Shunamite, a chamber furniſhed for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.10. that rather with prophane <hi>Tobiah,</hi> they will chamber themſelves in the courts of the houſe of GOD, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 13.7. and with <hi>Oreb</hi> and <hi>Zeeb,</hi> take to themſelves the houſes of GOD in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.12. So farre from paying Tithes of all, with <hi>Abraham;</hi> yea, of the ſpoiles gotten in warre, to the Prieſts of the high GOD, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.2. that they will rather ſpoile them, yea, GOD himſelfe in Tithes and Offerings, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. To ſhew therefore that theſe mens wayes are as much abominable to JEHOVAH, as they are different from his wayes, he prayeth that where they would bring a curſe, he would give a bleſsing; where they would devoure, hee would defend; where they would diminiſh, he would multiply; where they would ſpoile, he would protect; and addeth this imprecation againſt ſuch, <hi>Smite through the loines of them that riſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other queſtion is, why he rather prayeth not for a bleſſing from God upon their labours, then an acception of their labours by God? Since, <hi>Except the Lord build the houſe, their labour is in vaine that build it, Pſal.</hi> 125.1. Except he give increaſe, <hi>Pauls</hi> planting, &amp; <hi>Apollo's</hi> watering, is nothing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7. Except hee open the heart, as he did <hi>Lydia's, Act.</hi> 16.14. their ſpeaking to the eare is but a beating of the aire; for, he hath his chaire in heaven,<note n="(h)" place="margin">Cathedram <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> coel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> habet, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> who teacheth the hearts <hi>(k).</hi> The anſwer wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may be, that <hi>Moſes</hi> prayeth rather here for an accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Levies</hi> labour by GOD, as being their proper &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar good, than for a bleſſing upon their labours; which is their peoples good committed to them. For although
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:444:7"/>
               <hi>Levi,</hi> the LORDS meſſenger, muſt ſo unfainedly deſire in his heart the ſalvation of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> that in the fervency of his zeal, he could be content, with <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be razed out of GODS Book for them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. With <hi>Paul,</hi> be willing to be ſeparated from Chriſt for them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3. Although their ſtanding faſt in the LORD, muſt be the life, and the joy of his heart, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.8. That hee may rejoyce in the day of the LORD, that he hath not run in vaine, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.16. Although every ſoule that he ſaveth, muſt be his crowne of rejoycing, his glory and joy in the preſence of Chriſt at his comming, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.19, 20. Yet ſhall <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> as well receive his crowne for preaching vengeance againſt diſobedient <hi>Herod,</hi> as for winning converts to come to his baptiſme, and profeſſe reſurrection of life, <hi>Luk</hi> 3. And we are unto GOD the ſweet ſavour of Chriſt, not only in them that are ſaved, but alſo in them that periſh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. And although we labour in vaine in the world, and ſpend our ſtrength for nought: yet is not our work unregarded before God, neither ſhall it paſſe unrewarded, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.4. Hee prayeth therefore for this acceptation, as being their ſpeciall good for whom he ſpecially prayeth.</p>
            <p>To come then to the anatomizing, the unfolding of this Text. We have here <hi>honos Levitarum,</hi> the <hi>Levites</hi> honour, <hi>&amp; onus Levitarum,</hi> the <hi>Levites</hi> duty: a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance wherewith <hi>Levi</hi> muſt bee ſupported, and ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and a work wherewith he muſt be burthened. We have here, what JEHOVAH (who giveth liberally to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that asketh of him, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5.) is invocated to doe for him, <hi>To bleſſe his ſubſtance.</hi>] What his Maſter, to whom he ſtandeth or falleth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.4. is intreated fabourably to accept from him, <hi>Accept the worke of his hands.</hi>] What muſt deſcend from JEHOVAH to <hi>Levi?</hi> a bleſſing upon his ſubſtance. What muſt aſcend and come up in remembrance before JEHOVAH from <hi>Levi?</hi> an acceptable worke. In a word, all is comprehended
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:444:8"/>in a two fold petition. Firſt, for a bleſsing to be powred downe upon <hi>Levies</hi> ſubſtance from JEHOVAH. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for an acceptation of <hi>Levies</hi> worke by JEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VAH. In the former wee have either the author from whom the bleſsing muſt come, <hi>Bleſſe God;</hi> or the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject on which it muſt come, <hi>ſubſtance;</hi> amplified by the property, <hi>his ſubſtance.</hi> In the later wee have againe, firſt, an intimation of a worke to be performed by <hi>Levi, the worke of his hands:</hi> ſecondly, a ſupplication for the acceptation of it, <hi>accept the worke of his hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To beginne with the firſt, the author from whom this bleſsing muſt come, is he who <hi>openeth his hand; and filleth with his bleſſing every living thing, Pſal.</hi> 145.16. even the LORD: <hi>bleſſe Lord</hi>] In this particular then as in capitall letters, like to that viſion of <hi>Abacuk,</hi> ſo plaine, that he may runne that readeth it, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.2. We have this leſion, that the LORD is an ever-ſpringing, an ever-ſtreaming fountaine, from which all good gifts ſpring and flow upon every thing: and that this King of Kings and LORD of LORDS, is as that tree ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in a dreame, having in it meat for all, under the boughes whereof the beaſts of the field had ſhadow, in the boughes whereof the fowles of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven dweit, and of which all fleſh was fed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. And as on the one ſide affliction commeth not out of the duſt, neither doth miſery ſpring out of the ground, <hi>Job</hi> 5.6. but whatſoever evill is done in the City (<hi>malum poena;</hi> the evill of puniſhment) it is the LORD that doth it, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6. For whereas there are two kindes of evill; ſin, and the puniſhment of ſin<note n="(l)" place="margin">Cum ſint due genera malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, peccatum &amp; p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, &amp;c. <hi>Aug. contr. Adimant. Manich.</hi>
               </note>: ſinne belongeth not unto GOD, the puniſhment of ſinne belongeth unto him as the avenger: ſo on the other ſide, not onely promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but every good gift, commeth neither from the eaſt, nor weſt, nor from the ſouth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.6. <hi>but it is from above, and commeth downe from the Father of lights, Jam.</hi> 1.17. and it is a generall interrogatory to bee miniſtred
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:444:8"/>unto every one, <hi>What haſt thou that thou haſt not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. The voice of the naturall man who placeth his perfection in himſelfe, is, By the ſtrength of mine hands I have done this, and by my wiſedome, for I am prudent, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Is not this great Babylon that I have built by the might of my power? Dan.</hi> 4.30. His owne power, his owne mighty power. But they that are taught in the Schoole of grace, have learned to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve with their hearts, and confeſſe with their mouths, that it is the LORD that giveth, <hi>Job.</hi> 1.21. that becauſe GOD hath dealt graciouſly with them, they have all things, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.11. that all things come of GOD, all the ſtore that they have commeth of his hand, and all is his owne, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.14, 16. Let us beware then (belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) of ſacrificing to our nets, of burning incenſe to our drags, <hi>Abac.</hi> 1.16. But as all things are of him, ſo to him let us give glory for all things, as the Apoſtle cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleth them together, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.36. And let us be as mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to remember, as forward to receive; as ready with our Hallelu-jahs after deliuerance, as with our Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nahs in the time of trouble; as ready with our <hi>Quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribuanous? What ſhall I render unto the Lord? Pſal.</hi> 116: after benefits received; as with our <hi>Domine miſere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi>'s, <hi>God be mercifull unto us, and bleſſe us, Pſal.</hi> 65.1. in our woes and wants: as ready to fall downe at JESUS feet, and give thankes after cleanſing, as afore to cry out, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, maſter have mercy upon us, Luke</hi> 17.13.</p>
            <p>But I cannot <hi>figere pedem hîc;</hi> I haſten from the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this bleſsing, to the object about which it is converſant, a ſubſtance, wealth, riches, (ſo much the word imports) and that ſuch as is his, not others; his owne peculiar, not other mens almes or voluntary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, to be given and taken away at pleaſure; his in juſtice, as his proper right, not his by way of gratuity, and at other mens courteſie; for ſo ſerving at the Altar would ſoone come to ſtarving at the Altar. But becauſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:444:9"/>the Prieſts, and all the whole Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> were to have none inheritance in the land of Iſrael, nor any part among them, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.20. nor to ſhare with their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, in dividing the land by lot among the Tribes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.1, 2. let us examine a little what this ſubſtance of <hi>Levies</hi> was, what in the whole was the portion of <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſeed, that were to miniſter unto GOD in the Prieſts office, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.1. of the Levites, that were appointed over the Tabernacle of the Teſtimony, to doe ſervice in it, <hi>Num.</hi> 1.50. Firſt then, although the land was not divided amongſt them, as to the other Tribes, yet had they (in all likelihood) in the Cities, and ſubur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane grounds aſsigned unto them, as much as the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the greateſt Tribe came unto. For the fourty eight Cities, which the children of Iſrael were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to give them to dwell in, with the Suburbs for the Cities round about them, reaching two thouſand cubits on every ſide from every City, <hi>Num.</hi> 35.4, 5, 6. muſt in all probability equall the portion of any other Tribe, in ſo little a land as that was, which by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romes</hi> deſcription<note n="(m)" place="margin">Hierom. Epi. ad Darda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> did containe but in length from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba</hi> an hundred and ſixty miles, in breadth from <hi>Joppe</hi> to <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> about fourty ſix miles. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, beſides this glebe wherewith they were indowed, they had all the tenth in Iſrael, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.21. even all the Tithes of Corne, Wine, Oyle, Fruits. Herds and Flocks, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30, 32. Thirdly, they had every thing which opened the matrice in all fleſh, whether of men or beaſts, the firſtlings of Kine, Sheepe, and Goats, not to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed; the firſtborne of Men to bee redeemed at five ſhekels, and the firſtlings of the other beaſts to be redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at the Prieſts eſtimation, with a fift part put to it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.19, 20. <hi>Num.</hi> 18.15, 16. <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.27. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 10.36. Fourthly, they had the firſt fruits, even whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was ripe in the Land, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.13. the firh fruits of their Corne, Wine, Oyle, the firſt fruits of the fleeces of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:444:9"/>their Sheepe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.4. the firſt fruits of all manner of Trees, and of their very dough for a bleſsing upon the reſt, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.30. <hi>Nehem,</hi> 10.35, 37. Fiftly, they had all Oblations and Vowes, even every devoted thing in Iſrael, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.18, 14, 19. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.29, 30. Sixtly, they had every meat offering, every ſinne offering, every treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe offering, every heave offering, every ſhake offering, and the ſhew bread, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.9, 10. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.29. <hi>Levit.</hi> 24.9. Seventhly, of Sacrifices euchariſticall, the breaſt and the ſhoulder, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Levit.</hi> 7.31, 32. of other Sacrifices, the ſhoulder, the two cheekes, and the maw, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.3. and of whole burnt Sacrifices, the skinne, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> 7.8. And laſt of all, all the males among them muſt three times a yeare appeare before the LORD, in the place which he ſhould chooſe, and not come empty han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but every one was to give as he was able, according to the bleſsing of the LORD which he had given him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.16. This was the matter of their maintenance, being in reſpect of the quantity very large and liberall, and for the manner of it alſo, it was very honourable, for all theſe duties were to bee brought yeare by yeare unto the houſe of God, <hi>Neh.</hi> 10.35, 37. that, (as<note n="(n)" place="margin">Lib. de prim. ſacerd.</note>
               <hi>Philo Judaus</hi> obſerveth) from thence the Prieſts and Levites might receive them as from the hands of GOD, and not bee upbraided by the people, as though they lived by them, and were their almeſmen, which is now riſe in the mouthes of rude and ignorant men: But GOD ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the mouthes of ſuch miſcreants, when hee ſaith, <hi>I have given the children of Levi all the tenth, Num.</hi> 18.20. I, whoſe the earth is, and the fulneſſe thereof, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.1. and not the children of men, to whom I have given the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.16. And if any for their owne eaſe were deſirous to redeeme any duty, and not to carry it to the LORDS houſe, (which to ſome that dwelt afarre off would have beene very cumberſome) they were to pay according to the Prieſts eſtimation, at all times, <hi>Levit.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:444:10"/>27.27. with the addition of a fift part; and not by any injurious and Church-robbing preſcription or cuſtome, a feather for a gooſe, as the change of the times hath made it amongſt us. And if any but through ignorance (for wilfull theft in civill matter was puniſhed with a fourefold reſtitution, <hi>Ex.</hi> 22.1. much more in the things of GOD) detained any thing either in whole or part, which was holy to GOD, he was to bring a ramme for an offering, to make good that which he withheld, and to adda fifth part, <hi>Levit.</hi> 5.15, 16. This both for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the manner was the ſubſtance of <hi>Levi,</hi> given, granted, aſſigned and confirmed to him, <hi>haredibus &amp; ſucceſſoribus in perpetuum,</hi> for their executing the Prieſts office, for their ſervice in the Tabernacle, for their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of <hi>Iacob Gods judgements, and Iſrael his law;</hi> and that not by man (by whom notwithſtanding any thing devoted to the LORD is moſt holy, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.28.) but by this JEHOVAH, who is implored here to bleſſe his ſubſtance; unto whom by an eternall right, before the Law, under the Law, and after the Law, all Tithes are holy, <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30. and ſo not onely his, as the whole earth is his by right of creation and preſervation, (for he hath founded it upon the ſeas, and eſtabliſhed it upon the floods, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.2. but by a propriety and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate right that he hath in them, as having ſeparated them from mans uſe to himſelfe, and allowed man none inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in them at all, no not of uſe and poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>Now to come home with this to our times, men, bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and fathers: Was this <hi>Levies</hi> ſubſtance? Was the LORD ſo bountifull to the Prieſts and Levites under the Law? And will he not be as liberall to thoſe whom he hath put apart to preach the Goſpel, and to ſerve him in the Goſpel of his Son? If the miniſtration of death, of condemnation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7, 9. received ſo plentifull and large a maintenance from the hand of God, no man that hath any underſtanding in the myſtery of Chriſt, can
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:444:10"/>deny, but he would be as open handed to the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life and of the ſpirit. And why ſhall not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles reaſoning <hi>à pari,</hi> that as they which miniſter about the holy things, live of the things of the Temple; and as they which wait at the Altar, are partakers of the things of the Altar; even ſo GOD hath ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 14. hold as well for the proportion and quantity of the maintenance, as for the juſt right and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to claime and receive it? ſo that from that very Scripture we may not onely ſhew, that as GOD and not any man gave the Tithes to <hi>Levi;</hi> ſo GOD and not man hath ordained, that the Preacher of the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel; not of the Diſciples goods, but of the Goſpel, as <hi>Theophylact</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">Non ex diſcipulorum facultatibus ſed ex Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio. <hi>Theophy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lact. in 1 Cor. 9</hi>
               </note> gloſſeth the words, not of the Diſciples goods, by way of voluntary contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or beggerly almes, but upon their owne goods got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by preaching of the Goſpel: for neither (as <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact</hi> ſaith there) doeſt thou yeeld them maintenance, but their owne induſtry maintaineth them<note n="(p)" place="margin">Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> emni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tute in alimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ntum ſubmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh as ſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria quaedam induſtria ipſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> alit.</note>; but alſo that as great a portion and proportion is due to him that preacheth the Goſpel, as to him that miniſtred in the Tabernacle, and ſerved at the Altar. And if as great, why not the ſelfe ſame in kinde for Tithes, Oblations, and vowed things (ſetting aſide the Sacrifices, and the like, which were meerly ceremoniall and ſhadowes of things to come, and are now abrogated by Chriſt the body and ſubſtance of them, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.) Since they were due to GOD long before the Law, as wee ſee in <hi>Abrahams</hi> giving Tithe of all to <hi>Melchiſedech Prieſt of the high God, Gen.</hi> 14. in <hi>Iacobs</hi> vowing of Tithes unto GOD, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. ſince there can be no better courſe for fulfilling that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Apoſtle, <hi>Let him that is taught in the word, communicate to him that teacheth, in all his goods or good things, Gal.</hi> 6.6. If in all his good things, why not by way of a tenth? ſince there can be no more equall courſe,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:444:11"/>any quantity above that being too little for the teacher to receive, and under it being too much for him that is taught to give. That Tithes are to bee given to GOD and his Miniſters, <hi>Abraham</hi> ſignifieth by his deeds, <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> by his promiſes, afterwards the Law ordaineth it, and all the holy Doctors mention it<note n="(q)" place="margin">Decimas Deo &amp; ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotibus eius dandas, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham factis, Iaacob promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis inſinuas, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inde lex ſtatuit, &amp; omnes Doctores ſancti comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morant. Walfr. Strabo de rebus Eccleſiaſticis</note>,</p>
            <p>But here,</p>
            <q>
               <l>The ſcorching Eaſt, the South winde loud doe bluſter,</l>
               <l>The Southweſt winde up all his ſtorme, doe muſter<note n="(r)" place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>â Euruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Notuſque ruunt, creber<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> procellis Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, &amp;c. Virg. id. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>The Tabernacles of Edom, and the Iſhmaelites: of Moab and the Hagarins, Gebal, Ammon, and Amalek, the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines, with the inhabitants of Tyre, Aſſur alſo is joyned with them, Pſal.</hi> 83.6, 7, 8. Polititians and Papiſts, Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes and Atheiſts, are confederate together againſt GOD and his Church, for the ſpoiling of him and it in Tithes and Offerings, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8. The Polititians plea, is, that <hi>Levi</hi> was in eſtimation as the tenth part of Iſrael, and therefore having none inheritance amongſt them, had the tenth for their inheritance, whereas our Clergy are not the tenth part, nay ſcarcely the fiftieth part of the Realme, ſo that they need leſſe maintenance, and it is enough to provide them of a competent ſtipend. Theſe men are wiſe to doe evill, can reaſon plauſibly, ſo long as they ſpeake Babylons Logicke, <hi>Downe with it, downe with it to the ground, Pſal.</hi> 137. But all their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings herein, are but perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt minds, and deſtitute of the truth, ſuppoſing that gaine is godlineſſe, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. And their mouthes may be eaſily ſtopped by anſwering them, that howſoever the Levites were the thirteenth Tribe, yet they were not the tenth nor thirteenth part in Iſrael, but at that time that GOD gave them the Tithes for the ſervice of the Tabernacle, the ſixtieth part. For when the other Tribes were numbred from twenty yeares old and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſuch as were able to beare armes were in number ſix hundred thouſand, three thouſand, five hundred and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:444:11"/>fifty, beſides thoſe which were either but twenty yeares old, or unfit for ſervice, who would have doubled the number at leaſt: but the Levites being reckoned from a month old and above, their number was twenty two thouſand; <hi>Num.</hi> 1. <hi>per totum,</hi> which was not much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ſixtieth part. At this day then the Clergy of England, and their families, being not leſſe than the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth part of the Reame, as large a portion (even in their owne reaſoning, out of their owne mouth will I judge them) is requiſite for them as for the Levites. But that fancied Chimaera, that <hi>individuum vagum</hi> of a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency, how ſhall it anſwer the Apoſtles rule of <hi>communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating in all their goods? Gal.</hi> 6.6. How ſhall it ſupply their want at all times? How ſhall there be any certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it? ſince by reaſon of the ebbing and flowing, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and falling of the prices of things, it is as impoſſible to ſet downe a competent ſtipend, as it is to make a coat for the Moone. Was not tenne pounds by the yeare as competent about an hundred yeares ſince, as an hundred pounds are now? and who knoweth not whether fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ages may not ſee as great alterations? Certainly theſe competencies have already brought our Livings to an impotency, and the yoke of preſcription and cuſtome in receiving our dues after the old rate, lieth ſo heavy on our neckes, that the more other men proſper, we pine; the more they flouriſh, wee fade; the more their eſtate increaſeth, the more ours diminiſheth.</p>
            <p>Now againe the Papiſts, and ſome of our owne ſide, that have not looked ſo narrowly into this truth as they might have done, hold Tithes not to be required by the Morall Law conſonant to the law of Nature, but by the Judiciall Law, and therefore now to ſtand or fall in the Church, as it ſhall pleaſe Saint <hi>Peters</hi> heire the Pope, (ſaith the one) or the ſupreme Magiſtrate, ſaith the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But here, both antecedent and conſequent, both aſſertion and inference halt downe right, and finde no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:444:12"/>reſt for the ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le of their foot in any place of Scripture. The antecedent, that Tithes are judicialls, for all Tithes are <hi>holy to the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Levit.</hi> 27.30. ſeparated by himſelfe from common uſe; but all judicialls are things in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſe, not ſeparated from man: Tithes therefore are not, cannot bee judicialls. The conſequence againe is lame, Tithes are judicialls, therefore now they may be retained or removed <hi>ad placitum.</hi> For is it not a recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved tenent amongſt many of our Divines<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Piſc. praefat. in Levit. Perk. caſes conſc. &amp;c.</note>, that thoſe judicialls which ſerve for the backing of the Morall Law, for puniſhing the breaches of it, namely, idolatry, witchcraft, blaſphemy, murther, adultery, theft, diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to parents, are ſtill alive, ſtand in force, or at leaſt have a ſurviving equity in them? If the reſt, why not this of Tithes, which is as a bulwarke to the firſt Table, which preſcribeth the worſhip of GOD, the manner and maintenance thereof?</p>
            <p>But this poſition of our latter Papiſts, is not ſo old as their Canon Law: It was firſt invented by the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Hale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Maſter, and <hi>Thomas A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi> the Scholar, and the reſt of that ranke. When <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Papa,</hi> had taken the Tithes from the Oxen, that either did or ſhould plough, <hi>Job</hi> 1. the Rectors of the Churches, to whom they were properly due; and had improperly given them to the Aſſes that fed by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents of Monks and Friers. Thoſe locuſts that had made the face of the Church more deſolate, than ever the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts of Egypt did the face of the country, by devouring every greene thing throughout their land, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10.15. That ſo his ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>criledge in exempting ſome of their orders, from paying Tithes of their grounds, where they were due, (as <hi>Alexander</hi> the third exempted the <hi>Ciſtercians</hi> Hoſpitalars, and Templars from payment of Tithes<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexander 3. Ciſtercien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> Hoſpitala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plario<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> decima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lutione exemit, Catal. teſt. verit. To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2.</hi> lib. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note>. <hi>John</hi> the fifteenth gave the like privilege to the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictine Monkes at <hi>Cuſinum</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">Leo <hi>Maiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> Hoſtienſ. Epiſe. lib. <hi>2.</hi> hiſt. ca. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>. And in appropriating Church livings to all their Covents, might the better bee ſalved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:444:12"/>Therefore, as in many other points; ſo in this there is warre betweene the Canoniſts and the Scholemen: the Canoniſts contending, that payment of Tithes is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by Gods commandement, againſt the opinion of the Schole Divines<note n="(*)" place="margin">Quod deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum ſolutio ex divino prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepto ſit ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a contra Theologorum ſententiam Ianſ. Concord. cap. <hi>83.</hi>
               </note>; for ſo the old Canon runnes. We admoniſh and command, that by no meanes they neglect to pay Tithes to God, which God himſelfe hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them to pay<note n="(*)" place="margin">Admone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus atque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipimus ne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimas omnino dare Deo negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, quas ipſe Deus dare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſituit, cauſ. <hi>16</hi> qu. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>. And the authority of the Scripture ſheweth, that Tithes were granted for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of piety<note n="(y)" place="margin">Decimas in uſum pieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> conceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s eſſe Canonica auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat. cauſ. <hi>16.</hi> qu. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>. The Schole-men on the other ſide ſtriving that they are but judicialls, and ſo laying them o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to the Popes power, to be alienated, transferred, and diſpoſed of by him at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>But the ſchiſmaticall and upſtart generation of the Browmiſts cry out, (and herein the whole world will as eaſily wonder after theſe beaſts, as after the beaſts men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.3.) that Tithes are ceremonies; (an opinion of yeſterday, ſcarclely deviſed an hundred years ſince) and therefore to be throwne headlong out of the Church of Chriſt, aſwell as all other ceremonies which Chriſt hath taken away and nailed to his croſſe, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14. Aſſuredly, if their aſſertion be juſtified, the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion cannot be denied. I pronounce with a free voice, faith <hi>S. Hierom</hi>
               <note n="(z)" place="margin">Libera vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce pronuntio ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ias Juda. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum &amp; perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ioſas eſſe &amp; mortiferas Chriſtianis. <hi>Hieron. Aug. epiſt. 11.</hi>
               </note>, that the ceremonies of the Jewes are both pernicious and deadly to Chriſtians. That which they cannot prove, let me in a word or two diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove. Ceremonies were ſhadowes of things to come, carrying with them an analogicall reſemblance of the things ſignified, as the ſhadow carryeth with it a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of the body, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. They were carnall rites, of holy, of heavenly things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10, 23. of ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelicall truth. Let them ſhew then the body, whereof they were ſhadowes; the holy things, the Evangelicall truth, whereof they were types; or elſe we muſt tell them that Tithes are no ceremonies. For, if the definition doth not agree to any thing, the thing defined
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:444:13"/>cannot agree to it<note n="(a)" place="margin">Cui non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit definitio, eidem non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit definitum Regula Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</note>. And ſince all theſe carnall rites were but to indure till the time of reformation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. it is more then marveilous, that the Church of Chriſt ever retaining Tithes in uſe ſince the Apoſtles time, could not ſee them to be dead elements; yea, deadly ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, till this generation aroſe. Oh, but they were given to the Levites for the ſervice of the Tabernacle, <hi>Num.</hi> 18.21. therefore ceremonies. But I ſhall make it appeare by and by, that Tithes were not then firſt inſtituted, but long before, even from the beginning, they were then only aſſigned to the Levites. Againe, the argument holds not to prove them ceremonies, becauſe given to the ſons of <hi>Levi</hi> for the ſervice of the Tabernacle: For what manner of reaſoning is this; their work was ceremoniall, therefore their wages ceremonies? May not I better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they were given to the Levites for their ſervice in the Tabernacle, which was not only ceremoniall, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, yea and more principally morall; reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, cauſing the people to underſtand the reading. <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.38. bleſſing and praiſing the GOD of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 16.4. and teaching of the people the Law of the LORD of Hoſts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.7. Therefore they were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall duties.</p>
            <p>But as when our Saviours diſciples had rehearſed to him the diverſe opinions of men concerning him; ſome ſaying that he was <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> ſome <hi>Elias,</hi> ſome <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah,</hi> or one of the Prophets: He asked them, Whom ſay yee that I am? <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.15. So happily having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to you the diverſity of opinions herein, ſome ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they are judiciall, ſome ceremoniall, ſome tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, ſome abominable, ſome one thing, ſome another, moſt of them ſhooting at one marke, to wreſt them out of the hands of GODS Miniſters, you are ready to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, But what ſai'ſt thou that they are? whether moral, ceremoniall, or judiciall? I am not (beloved) fearfull to anſwer you concerning this point, but doe reſolutely
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:444:13"/>profeſſe unto you, that they are neither ceremonies ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be rejected, nor judicialls indifferent, either to be retained or refuſed; but morall, being holy to the LORD by an eternall right, as well before and after the Law, as under it; and being by him ordained to be the portion of his Prieſts and Miniſters, as well before and after, as under the Law; ſo that that aſſertion, <hi>all Tithes are holy to the Lord, Levit.</hi> 27.30. is no way Leviticall, but containeth in it a perpetuall truth, and that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell may as lawfully claime the tenth of their peoples increaſe, as before and under the Law the Prieſts of the high GOD received them. For the making good whereof two points are to bee propoſed. Firſt, that Tithes were ever due, and paid before the law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Secondly, that they are now due in the time of the Goſpel: for from thence it muſt follow evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that howſoever in the Law they were ſpecially aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to the ſonnes of <hi>Levi,</hi> yet they had not then their beginning, but were ever the Lords and his Miniſters by a morall and perpetuall right. For the firſt, Tithes were ever due, and paid before the Law. As ſoone as ever we finde any mention of a Prieſt of GOD, we find paiment of Tithes to him, and that <hi>eo nomine,</hi> becauſe he was the Prieſt of GOD; <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> was Prieſt of the moſt high GOD, and <hi>Abraham</hi> gave him Tithes of all, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.19, 20. And this he did, not by voluntary contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but rather by neceſſary injunction; for ſuch a gift would rather have argued the ſuperiority and excellency to have beene in <hi>Abraham</hi> the giver, than in <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dek</hi> the receiver: whereas the Apoſtle would have us to conſider <hi>Melchiſedeks</hi> greatneſſe by <hi>Abrahams</hi> giving of Tithes to him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.4. Againe, the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed <hi>Abraham;</hi> importing, that he tooke it by lawfull authoritie, not as a free will offering. In this way of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> walketh his grandchilde <hi>Iacob,</hi> (who no doubt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:444:14"/>was taught by <hi>Abrahams</hi> pious direction to keepe the way of the LORD herein, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. and voweth pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tithes unto GOD, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.20. as acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that they were his right before the Law was given. But here Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and his ſide would faine wring this teſtimonie out of our hands, and conclude hence, that tithes are no morall duties, becauſe they were vowed; he himſelfe faith, it had beene an ungodly thing to vow Tithes, if he had beene abſolutely bound to pay them<note n="(b)" place="margin">Impium fuiſſet vovere decimas, ſi abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutè fuiſſet obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus eas ſolve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, Bellar. contr. <hi>5.</hi> l. cap. <hi>25.</hi> tom. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>: and great a Rabbi amongſt them as he, that a man may not vow a morall duty conditionally, as <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> here doth<note n="(c)" place="margin">Alphonſ. Toſtat. in Matt. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note>, if GOD would be with him, and keep him in his way, and give him bread to eate, and raiment to put on. But it ſeemeth they are readie with their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer before ever they looked on the Text. For <hi>Jacob</hi> voweth, and that conditionally, that if GOD will bee with him, &amp;c. the LORD ſhall bee his GOD, which I thinke they will not denie to bee a morall dutie: even here then is evidence enough, that morall duties may be vowed, that they may be vowed conditionally. And if morall duties may not be vowed, why doe the people of the Jewes enter into a covenant, and ſweare unto the LORD GOD of their fathers, to ſeeke him with all their heart, and with all their ſoule? 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.12, 13, 14. Why doth <hi>David</hi> bind himſelfe by an oath to keep Gods righteous judgements? <hi>I have ſworne, and will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, that I will keepe thy righteous judgements, Pſal.</hi> 119.106. Thus out of the mouth and deeds of two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes beyond all exception. <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> may this truth bee eſtabliſhed, that Tithes were held Gods right, and his Prieſts, in the law of Nature, before eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the law written. The perſwaſion whereof was by the law of Nature ſo ingraven in mens hearts, the practice of it in all poſsibilitie ſo diſperſed from <hi>Noah</hi> amongſt all people, that (as <hi>Feſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> ſaith<note n="(d)" place="margin">Decima quaque veteres diis ſuis offere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</note>) the old people offered all kinde of Tithes to their gods, as <hi>Cyrus</hi> overcomming
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:444:14"/>the Lydians offered all to <hi>Jupiter</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Heredot. Cli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>, and <hi>Bacchus</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming the Scythians, offered to him alſo<note n="(f)" place="margin">Te memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Gange, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toque oriento ſubacto, Primitias ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gno ſepoſuiſſe Iovt. Ovid. l. <hi>3.</hi> Faſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>They ſay when thou hadſt Ganges and the Eaſt o've<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne,</l>
               <l>Thou ſet'ſt apart for Jove the firſt fruits, as his owne.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And the ancient Romanes did vow Tithes to <hi>Hercules</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Macrob. Sat. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ca. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note>, yea the very barbarous Sabeans and Ethiopians ſold not their ſpices to the Merchants, before their Prieſts had laid out their tenth for their gods<note n="(h)" place="margin">Decimas deo ſacerdotes cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, necontè mercari licet. Plin. nat. hiſt. li. <hi>12.</hi> ca. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>. Thus have I examined and cleered the firſt point.</p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond, which is, that they are now due to GOD, and thoſe that ſerve him in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of his Sonne, ſince the aboliſhing of the Law of Ordinances. And here the great Cardinall and the Popiſh Champions (who when the doore muſt bee ſet open to unwritten traditions, can denie the Scripture to be full enough without traditions, to containe expreſſely the whole doctrine either concerning faith or manners, and that therefore traditions are requiſite<note n="(i)" place="margin">Scriptura non contiuet expreſsè totam doctrinam ſivo de fide, ſive de moribus, &amp;c. Bellarm. li. <hi>4.</hi> de verb. dei c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>: nay can with the like affection of pietie and reverence, receive and honour unwritten traditions, as all the bookes of the<note n="(k)" place="margin">Traditi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes non ſcriptas pari pieta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> affect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; reverentia ſuſcipere &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerari, ac om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes libros tam veteru quam novi Teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, Concil. Trid. Seſſ. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Old and New Teſtament) doe now call for an expreſſe precept in the new Law, ſpecifying Tithes to bee the Miniſters maintenance, an expreſſe precept, it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to have it in ſenſe, but we muſt have it in words; to have it by ſound conſequence and collection, but wee muſt have it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, word for word; and yet <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nazianzen</hi> ſaith, that thoſe things which are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the Scriptures, are alike to thoſe things which are written expreſſely<note n="(l)" place="margin">Perinde ſunt ea qua e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Scripturis colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur, atque ea quae ſcribun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note>. If I can then deduce it by good conſequence out of the New Teſtament, it ſhall be enough, though it be not written <hi>in totidem verbis &amp; ſyllabis.</hi> When the Apoſtle then mentioneth living of the Goſpel, and that ever ſo, as they which wait at the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:444:15"/>Altar are partakers of the Altar, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 13. when he urgeth communicating to our teachers in all our goods, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. wee may not here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>collatis teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis demonſtrare,</hi> (as <hi>Beza</hi> interpreteth it, <hi>Act</hi> 9.22.) by comparing teſtimonies of Scripture, by laying one place to another, ſhew, that this living of the Goſpell, this communicating in all our goods, ſhould bee now by the tenth, as being a courſe held before the Law, and under the Law, unleſſe man will be wiſer than his Maker, and deviſe a new way of living for them, of communicating to them, leaving the old which GOD had ſettled from the beginning of the world. And what ſhall become of that double honour, double maintenance, which the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that rule well are worthie of, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. if the portion of the Presbyters under the Goſpell come ſhort of the portion of the Prieſthood under the Law? for ſo to underſtand honour the next verſe there giveth us light, for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>The labourer is worthy of his reward;</hi> and accordingly Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> expoundeth honour to be maintenance, and underſtandeth by main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Tithes; adding alſo, What we have ſaid concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Tithes which heretofore were given by the people to the Prieſts and Levites, underſtand it alſo concerning the people of the Church<note n="(m)" place="margin">Quod de decimis dixim u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> qua olim daban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur à populo Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Levitis, in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae quoque populis intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gito.</note>. May we not finde here as good evidence in theſe teſtimonies for Tithes, as any where in the New Teſtament, for the perpetuall and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable obſervation of the ſeventh day (cried up with more than a Jewiſh rigour, by many not zealous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to diſcretion<note n="(n)" place="margin">See their abſurd poſitions in <hi>Rogers</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to Articles of Relig.</note>,) for the baptizing of infants, and many other truths, which are not expreſſed in the very letter, and ſo many words, but ſoundly and juſtly gathered out of the ſenſe and purpoſe of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? And what thinke wee of the Apoſtles reaſoning, <hi>Heb</hi> 7.6, 7, 8, 9. when he proveth <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and ſo Chriſts, which is all one, greater than the Leviticall: firſt, becauſe in <hi>Abraham Levi</hi> paid Tithes to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:444:15"/>
               <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> and ſo to Chriſt. Secondly, becauſe <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck</hi> is a Tith taker that liveth ſtill, and <hi>Levi</hi> is a Tith-taker that dieth. Doe not theſe conſectaries fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and flow from it? Firſt, that if <hi>Levi</hi> paid Tithes in <hi>Abraham,</hi> then they are originally no Leviticall cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, howſoever under the Law they were ſpecially aſſigned to him; for that is a croſſing of the Leviticall ordinances, which injoyne, that Tithes ſhould bee paid to <hi>Levi.</hi> Secondly, if before the Law Tithes were paid unto Chriſt in <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> (then hee receiveth them of whom it is witneſſed that hee liveth, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8.) why ſhould they not likewiſe be paid unto Chriſt in his Presbyters, after that law is aboliſhed: now they muſt live of the Goſpel, and being in his ſtead, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. are fitteſt to bee his receivers. Thirdly, if other things wherein <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> the type, and Chriſt the antitype agree, and are brought to prove his eternall Prieſthood, are ever true of him; as, that he is King of righteouſnes, King of peace, that he is without father or mother, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſcent; having neither beginning of dayes, nor end of life. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1.3. Why not this, hee ever taketh Tithes: ſince he receiveth Tithes of whom it is witneſſed that hee liveth, and ſince this paying of Tithes is produced with the reſt, to prove Chriſts eternall prieſthood.</p>
            <p>Againe, is not ſacrilege accurſed, and accurſed for ſin, not only in the old Teſtament, (it is a ſnare to to the man who devoureth that which is holy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.25.) but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the New? Thou that abhorreſt idols, doſt thou commit ſacrilege? <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. Is it not puniſhed as a capitall ſinne, not only in the one Teſtament, (in <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar, Dan.</hi> 5.) but alſo in the other? (In <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira, Act.</hi> 5.)? For the ſinne is ſo much the more grievous, by how much it cannot be committed, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.<note n="(o)" place="margin">Tantò gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius eſt pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quantò committinon poteſt niſi in Deum.</note> And ſo ſpeaketh <hi>Beza</hi> of <hi>Ananias</hi> ſin: To this ſacrilege there was added diffidence and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie: And ſo S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">Beza in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> whilſt he taketh away part
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:444:16"/>of that which he promiſed, he is condemned both of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege and fraud: of ſacrilege, becauſe he deceived God of his promiſe<note n="(q)" place="margin">Dum exeo quod promiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> partem ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trahit, ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gii ſimuleon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnatur &amp; fraudis: ſacrilegis quod Deum in pollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione fefelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. Ambr. ſer. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note>. Now if ſacrilege<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is the taking away of things deputed and conſecrated to GOD and his worſhip, being either ſuch things as God by expreſſe reſeruation hath conſecrated to himſelfe: or elſe ſuch as man hath conſecrated and ſet apart to him, be ſtill a ſinne under the Goſpel, ſtill make men guilty before God. How then ſhould not the payment of Tithes be a morall duty, ſtand ſtill in force under the Goſpel? ſince (as for mine owne part I take it) God hath conſecrated them to himſelf by an eternall right: which right he chaleng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, (<hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30. <hi>All Tith is holy unto the Lord.</hi>) At leaſt (as no man can deny) they are by the Lawes, not only of this Land, but almoſt of all Chriſtendome, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated unto God for the maintenance of his worſhip and miniſtery. And as the Scriptures are pregnant enough on our ſide to prove Tithes a morall duty, and now to be continued under the Goſpel. So in the primitive &amp; beſt times of the Church, the beſt of the Fathers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels underſtood, interpreted, and preſſed them ſo; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired them as a morall and Chriſtian duty: and for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a thouſand yeares it was never held in the Church, that they were either judiciall or ceremoniall. <hi>Origen,</hi> who was neere to the Apoſtles times, (there being but eighty foure yeares between <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſts death and his birth) urgeth the paiment of Tithes as a doctrine then received in the Church, and binding Chriſtians. How doth<note n="(r)" place="margin">Quomodo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundat iuſtitia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſtrapluſquam Scribarum &amp; Phariſaeorum, ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lli de fructibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> terra ſua guſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non audent, priuſquam pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> offerant, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Levitis deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae ſeparent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, &amp; ego nihil ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum faciens, fru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tibus terra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta abutar, ut Sacerdes neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, Levita igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, divinum al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare non ſentiat Orig. homil. <hi>11.</hi> in Num?</note> our righteouſneſſe abound more than the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, if they dare not taſte of the fruits of the earth, before they offer the firſt fruits to the Prieſts, and the Tithes be ſeparated for the Levites: and I doing none of theſe, ſhall ſo abuſe the fruits of the earth, that the Prieſts ſhall not know it, the Levit ſhall bee ignorant of it, GODS Altar ſhall not perceive it. And further, there he delivereth his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:444:16"/>for that point. I thinke it neceſſary that this Law ſhould be obſerved according to the letter<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Hane egole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem obſervart etiam ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> literam, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium puto.</note>: and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth our Saviours words (<hi>Mat.</hi> 23. <hi>Theſe things you ought to have done, and not to have left the other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done</hi>) to bee a precept no leſſe binding Chriſtians than Jewes. Thus did he hold them to be morall, found them in <hi>novalege.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Cyprian</hi> (whofe Martyredome fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout two hundred fifty nine yeares after Chriſt,) giveth us to underſtand, that Miniſters then lived of Tithes, then diſtributed to them by the Biſhops, who were the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Stewards of Church goods<note n="(t)" place="margin">In honore ſportulantium fratrum tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam decima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ex fructibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipientes. Ep. <hi>66.</hi> Sportula <hi>was the ſtipend al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Biſhop to the Presbyter.</hi>
               </note>: living (faith hee) of that honourable ſtipend, with their brethren, as they who received Tithes of the fruits of the earth. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> alſo preſſeth this payment and a reformation, when fault had been committed afore. Whoſoever ſhall call to minde in himſelfe, that he hath not faithfully payed his Tithes, let him now amend that which he hath failed in<note n="(u)" place="margin">Quicunque recogno verit in ſe, quod ſideliter non deder it deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, quomodo emendet quod. minu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fecit. Ambr. ſerm. <hi>34.</hi> in fer. quadrag.</note>. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo can finde footing in the new Teſtament for Tithes, when he expoundeth, <hi>Give unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods, Mat.</hi> 22.21. Tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> Tithes to GOD<note n="(x)" place="margin">Caeſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, decima deo. Hom. <hi>48.</hi> tom. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>. When he ſaith againe, Set apart the Tithes, although that bee a ſmall matter; for it is ſaid that the Phariſees gave Tithes: And what ſaith the LORD, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe your righteouſneſſe exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, you cannot enter into the Kingdome of Heaven</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">Decimas exime quanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parum ſit, dictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt enim quia Phariſas deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas dabant: &amp; quid art domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, niſi abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daverit, &amp;c. Idem in Pſal. <hi>146.</hi>
               </note>. And it ſeemeth that this was no new thing done under the Sun in his time, by that which he faith againe, Our Anceſtors did therefore abound with all ſtore, becauſe they gave Tithes to GOD, and paid their Tribute to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> But now becauſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion hath decreaſed, exactions have increaſed: wee will not give the tenth part to GOD, and now all is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away; that which Chriſt cannot have, <hi>Caeſar</hi> will<note n="(z)" place="margin">Maiores no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ideo coptis omnibus abundabant quia doe decimas dabant, &amp; Caeſars cenſum reddebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, modo autem quia deceſſit devotic, acceſsit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndictio fiſci, nolumus partiricum deo decima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dòauté tollitur tetu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: hec tollit fiſcus, quod non accipit Chriſtus. Id. hom. <hi>48.</hi> inter <hi>50</hi> ſer.</note>.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:444:17"/>The time would faile me if I ſhould produce other teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies out of Fathers. Councels, Oecumenicall and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall, lawes Eccleſiaſticall and Imperiall: all of them acknowledging paiment of Tithes to bee a morall duty, commanding them now to be paid to the Church. The one of the ſecond Councell held at <hi>Matiſcon, anno</hi> 586. ſhall ſerve for all<note n="(a)" place="margin">Leges divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na conſulentes Sacerd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tibus &amp; Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtris Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rum pro ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a portio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, omus populo praceyerunt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cim as fruct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um ſuorum locis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres praſtare, ut nullo labore im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedite per res illegitimas, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>alibus poſſis vacare Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, quas le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum congeries longis tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus cuſtodivit intemeratas. Vnde ſtatuimus &amp;c.</note>. The Lawes of God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for Prieſts and Miniſters of the Churches, for their hereditary portion, have commanded all people to pay the Tithes of their fruits to the holy places: that being no wayes hindred by unlawfull things, they might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their ſpirituall offices: Which lawes the Chriſtian Church hath a long time kept undefiled. Whereupon we ordaine that all people ſhall pay their Eccleſiaſticall Tithes. And ſo I conclude with that of <hi>Junius,</hi> that Tithes have beene holy to God by all right ſince the memory of man<note n="(b)" place="margin">Decima iut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns poſt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num memoria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Deo fuerunt ſacra.</note>: And that it was ſacrilege in the Pope at firſt, to appropriate them to Monks and Friers, from the labouring Oxen: no better in ſecular perſons at the diſſolution of the Abbies to invade them, in Patrons to ſet them to ſale, to detaine any glebe or Tithes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to God: In Pariſhioners, either by ſecret pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, or pretended cuſtomes, to defraud the Miniſter of them: And that God is much robbed in our Church, partly by preſcriptions and cuſtomes, which ſnatch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſomewhat from every Church in our Realme; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by impropriations, which of nine thouſand two hundred, eighty and foure Pariſh Churches, (for that is the juſt number in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Brit. pag. <hi>262.</hi>
               </note>) have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured three thouſand, eight hundred ninety five, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the halfe in number, but farre above the halfe in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and goodneſſe. God put it into the hearts of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Biſhops, Deanes, and Chapiters, and Colledges, (who hold many of them ſtill in the right of the Church) to proved ſo conſcionably for thoſe that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in them; that whilſt they ſerve at the Altar, they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:444:17"/>may not ſtarve at it. But to dreame of any reſtitution of them from the Lay poſſeſſors, (unleſſe it bee here and there one, like a berry or two in the top of a bough, whoſe heart God hath touched) were as the Poet ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a dreame of a ſhadow. When we have ſaid and reaſoned all that we can, they have againſt us one argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for themſelves, <hi>ab utili,</hi> which we ſhall never ſolve nor diſſolve. In this caſe let me ſay to you as <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaid to the Prophets that propheſied, <hi>Behold the veſſels of the Lords houſe ſhall now ſhortly be brought againe from Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</hi> If we be Prophets, let us now make interceſſion to the LORD of Hoſts, that the veſſels that are left in the houſe of the LORD, goe not to <hi>Babylon, Jer</hi> 27.15, 16. For as the Iſraelites of old cryed, ſo may we; The ſword of the LORD and of <hi>Gideon, Judg.</hi> 7.20. It is the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our God, and the Piety of our gracious King, that yet preſerveth to us from thoſe Evening wolves, theſe,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Relliquias Danaum, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> immitis Achillis</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Virg. Aene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>id. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>That I have ſo long dwelt upon this point and petition, <hi>The bleſſing of the Levites ſubſtance,</hi> I may ſay to theſe evill times whereinto wee have falne, as <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in another caſe, Ye have compelled me. In the next petition, which is another requeſt for an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the worke of his hands. I will briefly touch the firſt branch, which is an intimation of a worke to be performed by him, as being moſt pertinent to this time and perſonshere preſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Accept the worke of his hands.]</hi> There lay a neceſſity upon man, even in his innocency, to labour in an honeſt calling: The LORD GOD tooke <hi>Adam,</hi> after he had made him, and put him into the garden of <hi>Eden</hi> to dreſſe it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.15. But when man had ſinned againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and forfeited his ſtate in that Paradiſe of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, when his labour ſhould have been with pleaſure, without defatigation; hee was turned out into the wide
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:444:18"/>world; into the earth, curſed for his ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.17. In which with the ſweat of his browes, even with difficult labour, paine, and ſorrow, hee muſt eat his bread, and get his living. For now all his dayes are ſorrow, and his travell grief, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.13. And now labour lieth on him not only as a duty, teſtifying his obedience, wherein hee muſt imitate the holy Angels, who are created of GOD to be miniſtring ſpirits, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. Yea, his heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who laboured in the beginning of time, in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of all things, and at this time; and to the end of times; worketh in the preſervation of all his creation, <hi>John</hi> 5.17. but alſo as puniſhment of his diſobedience; <hi>Man is borne unto labour, as the ſparks flie upward, Job</hi> 5.7. And this working with his hands, is the diſcharging of the duties of that calling wherein GOD hath ſet him, as the LORD hath called every man, ſo let him worke 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.17.</p>
            <p>Now this worke of <hi>Levies</hi> hand, was (that I may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the things that differ) either ceremoniall, or morall. The ceremoniall was to miniſter in the Prieſts office, <hi>Ex.</hi> 28.1. to offer gifts and ſacrifices, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.3. to be over the Tabernacle of the Teſtimonie, over all the veſſels thereof, and all things that belong unto it; <hi>Numb.</hi> 1.10. The morall was to thanke and praiſe the GOD of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 16.4. and 23.31. to bleſſe the children of Iſrael in GODS name, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.8. to read in the book of the Law diſtinctly, give the ſenſe, and cauſe the people to underſtand the reading, <hi>Neh.</hi> 8.8. to ſhew the people the ſentence of judgement in hard matters, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 19.8. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.23, 24. to exhort them in warre, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20.23. to teach them at all times the Law of the LORD of Hoſts; and to walk before the Lord in uprightneſſe, that ſo they might turne many ſtom their iniquities, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.6, 7. Now the firſt of theſe, the ceremoniall worke, was to indure but till the time of reformation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.10. the faſtning of that hand
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:444:18"/>writing of ordinances, to the croſſe of Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. that law being changed, and aboliſhed, this work of the Prieſthood is aboliſhed alſo. The other worke, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, is to continue, though not in the tribe of <hi>Levi;</hi> yet in thoſe Prophets, Paſtors, and teachers that Chriſt gave for the perfecting of the Saints, the worke of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and the edifying of his body, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. till the end of the world; the appearing of JESUS CHRIST, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 6.14. This worke in regard of the authority by which, or maſter for whom it is don, is called <hi>the Lords work.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.10. in regard of the dignity of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a good or godly worke, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. and the workemen thereof labourers together with God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. in regard of the greatnes of it; a worke hardly to be fitted with a workman, who is ſufficient for theſe things? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. it is <hi>onus vel ipſis angelis formidan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dum</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Bernard.</note>; a burthen to be feared of the very Angels. <hi>Ars eſt artium regimen animarum</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Gregor. in paſt. par. <hi>1.</hi> ca. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>; the government of Soules is the art of arts.</p>
            <p>Now beloved Brethren of the Clergie, the chariots of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.12. Since the lines are falne to us in this pleaſant place, ſuffer, I pray you, a few words of exhortation. As, then, wee have taken upon us the Miniſteriall office and worke: ſo that miniſtery which we have received from the LORD, let us fulfill in the LORD, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.17. even doe the worke of Evangeliſts, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 4.5. And ſince wee are Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours for Chriſt; let us in Chriſts ſtead pray our people to be reconciled to GOD, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. ſhew all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Chriſt to the houſhold of faith, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.27. Since we are watchmen ſet over the houſe of GOD, let us take heed unto our flocks; watching night and day, in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and out of ſeaſon, for the Soules committed to our charge, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17. For if all ought to watch, (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) much more ought the ſhepheards<note n="(g)" place="margin">Stomnes vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilare debent, multo magis pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es. Bern. de vigil. paſtor.</note>. If he ſo laboureth and watch who feedeth <hi>Labans</hi> ſheepe,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:444:19"/>(ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Baſil</hi>); with what labour, and what watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ought he to beſtirre himſelfe, who feedeth GODS ſheepe<note n="(h)" place="margin">Siſic laborat &amp; vigilat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us paſcit oves L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, quanto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a bort, quantiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue vigiliisd be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendere, qui paſcit oves D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>? Baſil, hom. de pae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st.</note>. Since we are GODS ſtewards, let us give to every one of his houſhold their portion in due ſeaſon, <hi>Luk</hi> 12.42. For if hee who provideth not for them of his owne houſe, the bread that periſheth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.27. hath denyed the ſaith, and is worſe than an Infidell, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. Much more is hee to bee accounted ſo, who provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not for thoſe of GODS houſe, the bread that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth to eternall life. The rulers ſlackneſſe is their charges wrong<note n="(i)" place="margin">Incuria pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſits eſt insuria depoſits. Hieron. Epiſt. ad Furia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>. Since we are ſowers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let us go forth to ſowe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.3. not to reap only: ſince planters, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. let us ingraft in the minds of the faithfull, that word which is able to ſave their ſoules, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21. Since waterers, let us water thoſe tender plants, that are plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the courts of the LORD; and let it not be our fault that the LORDS field ſhould ſeeme to be curſed with the curſe of the mountaines of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> upon which neither dew nor raine fell, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. Since builders in the houſe of GOD, let us ſo build up the houſhold of faith upon Chriſt Jeſus the corner ſtone, that they may grow unto an holy temple in the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21. Since men of GOD, let us quit our ſelves like men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13. preach the word, bee inſtant, reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long ſuffering and doctrine, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2. Since the ſalt of the earth, let us have ſalt in our ſelves, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.50. and let all our ſpeech be ſo ſeaſoned with ſalt, that it may miniſter grace to our hearers, <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6. Since Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the LORD of Hoſts, let our lips preſerve knowledge, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. let us bring glad tidings of good things to our auditors, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. And ſince wee are labourers in his vine-yard, let us goe into it; and that not only to feed there, but alſo and much more to labour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.4. Let us not be dumbe dogges, ſuch as cannot, or will not barke; and who have need that Chriſt ſhould caſt out of them that dumbe divell, <hi>Luk</hi> 11.14. nor dead
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:444:19"/>idols, who have mouthes, and ſpeake not. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.5. Nor Paſtors derived by Antiphraſis, a <hi>non paſcendo,</hi> from not feeding<note n="(k)" place="margin">Vt monia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non movendo.</note> or of <hi>paſcor paſceris,</hi> to be fed only: For when they do not feed, but are fed themſelves, they are not derived from <hi>paſco,</hi> to feed; but from <hi>paſcor,</hi> to be fed<note n="(l)" place="margin">Cum enim non paſcant ſed paſcantur, non agrave; paſco der<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed à paſcor paſcerit. Vetus poema per Illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum, de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt. ſtatu Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae.</note>. Let not thoſe complaints light upon us which Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> darted out againſt the Clergy of his time, ſaying, that they were in habit Clergy men; in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after gaine, men of the world; but in work, neither: that they laboured not as other men; but whereas all ſtates of men have ſome labour, and ſome pleaſure, that they by a new cunning dividing betweene theſe, have choſen that which is delightfull in every thing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected that which is diſpleaſing<note n="(m)" place="margin">Eos eſſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitu Clericos, quaſtis munda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, actu neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s; in labore hominum non eſſe, ſed cum cuncts ſtatus hominum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid habeant laboris, &amp; ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid voluptatis, Clericos inter haec novo quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam artificio diſcernentes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quod dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat in quolibet elegiſſe, &amp; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quod mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat reſpuiſſe di. <hi>3.</hi> de conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione.</note>. Let the Pope onely take this privilege to himſelfe, that though he draw mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of ſoules after him to hell, yet no man may preſume to ſay to him; Sir, why doſt thou doe ſo<note n="(n)" place="margin">Diſtinct. <hi>40</hi> in decret.</note>. But let us take heed unto our ſelves, to reading, or exhortation and doctrine, that we may ſave our ſelves, and them that heare us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.26.</p>
            <p>But above all things, let mee put you in minde of one thing, that wee bee not onely ſuch as have the light of knowledge, but ſuch alſo as are indued with the fire of zeale; that our lips may not only preſerve knowledge, but alſo (that which the LORD requireth in the Tribe of <hi>Levi, Mal.</hi> 2.6, 7.) that we may walke with GOD in peace and equity; that we may weare upon our breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plates, not only the Vrim of light and knowledge, but alſo the Thummin of integrity and good converſation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.30. that we may alwaies enter into the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of the LORD with our golden bells, the ſound of preaching; and Pomegranates, the fruit of good living, (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Gregory</hi> interpreteth it<note n="(o)" place="margin">Greg. lib. <hi>1.</hi> epiſt. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note>) mingled together, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.33, 34. that we who teach others, may teach our ſelves, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.21. who preach to others, may not our ſelves be caſt-awayes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27. For it belongeth to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:444:20"/>GODS Prieſts, not only to teach, but alſo to do the laws that they may not only teach their people and flocke committed to them with words, but alſo with exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples<note n="(p)" place="margin">Sacerdotum. enim eſt propriè non ſolum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere ſed &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, legem, ut nequaquam verbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubjectos ſibi populos, &amp; creditum gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, ſed exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis doceant. Hieron. in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note>. This is the beſt harmony of all, when the Prieſts minde, hand, and tongue agree<note n="(q)" place="margin">Haeceſt pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherrima har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia, quando Sacerdotis mens, manus, lingua, concordant. Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſt. ad Nepo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. But on the other ſide, it is nothing to preach the truth, if the heart diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree from the tongue<note n="(r)" place="margin">Praedicare veritatem nil eſt, ſi cor lingua diſſentiat. Aug. in Pſal. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note>: Nay, if we could ſpeak with the tongue of men, ſhould be ſo skilfull in Oratory, that we could at our pleaſure lift up, advance, amplifie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate, and as it were by an inchanting power of elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, turne any thing into what ſhape and habite wee would; and ſo ſubtile in diſputing, that we could worke any thing out of any thing: if wee could ſpeake with the tongue of Angels, (if there were any angels tongues<note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Si quae ſint Angelorum lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua. Hieron.</note>, for the words are to be underſtood hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolically) if we had prophecy, the gift of interpreting the Scriptures, and knew not ſome few, but all myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; even the whole myſtery of godlineſſe: and had not ſome little knowledge, but all; even not only the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this world, and the Princes thereof, which come to nought, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. So that with <hi>Solomon</hi> wee could ſpeak of plants from the Cedar which is in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus, to the Hyſſope which groweth upon the wall: and of beaſts, and birds, and creeping things, and fiſhes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4.33. but alſo the wiſedome of GOD hid in a myſterie, and had not charity: not only theſe excellent gifts are to be accounted nothing, but we our ſelves are nothing, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1, 2. To ſuch Phariſees who ſay and doe not, that ſame ſong of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bernard,</hi> not pleaſant but profitable, muſt be ſung.<note n="(t)" place="margin">Monſtroſa res eſt gradus ſummus, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uimus infimus, ſedes prima &amp; vita ima, lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua magnilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua &amp; manus o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſa, ſermo multus &amp; fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus nullus, vultus gravis &amp; actus levis, caput canum, &amp; cor vanum, facies rugoſa &amp; lingua nugoſa, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngens autoritas &amp; nutan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtabilitas, Lib <hi>2.</hi> de conſiderat.</note> It is a monſtrous thing to have an high degree, and a baſe minde; the chiefe ſeat, and a lewd life; a tongue ſpeaking great words, and an idle hand; much ſpeech, and no fruit; a grave countenance, and a light carriage; a gray head, and an idle heart; a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:444:20"/>wrinkled face, and a trifling tongue; great authority, and a tottering ſtability. To grow to an end then, let us ſo take heed to our ſelves, that we may live well, and to our doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. that we may inſtruct our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple committed to our charge: Let us ſo ſhine as bright ſtars in the militant Church, (that is in <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation<note n="(u)" place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>11.</hi> in Matt.</note>, Let. us ſo teach that men may not only hear our words, but alſo ſee our good works) that at length wee may ſhine as bright ſtarres in the triumphant Church for ever and ever, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. And let us ſo joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe, and teach the leaſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.19. the greateſt, all the commandements of GOD, that wee may bee called great in the Kingdome of grace; may be found heirs in the Kingdome of glory, and ſit with Chriſt in his Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. To whom with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Holy Ghoſt, three Perſons, one GOD, and King eternall, immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, inviſible, and onely wiſe, bee Honour and Glory, for ever and ever. AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
